# **SUSHMITA BISWAL**

## **Data Scientist**

sushmita.biswal5@gmail.com +91-9811451358 Hyderabad, India https://www.linkedin.com/in/sushmitabiswal-3a028026/

## **Achievements**

- Winner of Deloitte analytics summit2018
- Published thought piece on "Strategies for stemming the opioid epidemic"
- Published report Using advanced analytics to drive regulatory reform'
- Published paper "Satellite data classification using open source support" in journal of Indian society of remote sensing September 2013.

# Skills

- R Programming
- Python
- Tableau
- SQL

# Machine Learning

- NLP, sentiment analysis
- Text summarization
- Regression
- Clustering, decision trees and random trees
- Knowledge of Neural Networks, statistics and Time series
- https://github.com/sbiswal1/ Text

## **GIS**

- Data Scraping from Google map API and geospatial data manipulation
- Created water depth maps using geology, water depth in the well

## **Professional Summary**

Data Scientist having 8 years of experience in data analysis, geospatial data analysis and providing smart insights for business solutions. I bring interdisciplinary skills of machine learning and GIS including programming skills in R, Python to derive interesting story from data. My working day would require data scraping, creating data mines, processing and analyzing and visualize interesting findings. Satellite image processing and object recognition are some interesting addition to my profile.

### **Work Experience**

#### Deloitte

**Data Scientist** 

Jan 2017 - Till date

- Delivered around 5 projects using data modelling and developed client ready analysis as a part for successful Deloitte thought wares
- Responsible for providing data driven insights for cross industry publications like consumer & retail, energy sector, healthcare and public sector
   Developed models using machine learning algorithms and NLP to explain drivers to
- certain industry aligned problem.

  Implemented data ingestion from API, transformation of both unstructured and
- structured data
   Produced reusable scripts to automate repetitive workflows including optimization
- strategies
- Implemented EDA, NLP, random forest, regression, clustering based model
- Published work for Deloitte insights 'Strategies for stemming the opioid epidemic' and 'Using advanced analytics to drive regulatory reform'
- NLP work for millions of regulations and over half a million pages recognized over 20 clients and presented at White House US.

# Risk Management Solutions

Sep 2014 - Jan 2017

Senior Analyst

- Developed predictive model and analyzed massive data for core model development team
- Delivered data layers using regression analysis and Geostatistics
- Predicted ground water depth and performed interpolation to create depth maps
- Used Kriging for spatial interpolation to create water depth map layers
- Contributed significantly to geology spatial mapping for core earthquake risk model

#### Risk Management Solutions

Apr 2012 - Sep 2014

**GIS** Engineer

- Developed and analyzed data inventories for US, Japan and New Zealand
- Performed extraction, transformation and compiling massive unstructured data into structured databases
- Used weighted overlay method to distribute financial values at different administrative layers and heuristics to classify data related to buildings/parcels

#### TERI University

Aug 2011 – May 2012

**Project Consultant** 

- Was involved in ISRO-DST, LULC PROJECT of Land use and land cover dynamics and impact of human dimensions in Indian river basins Worked for development of land use databases and collection of ancillary data for Chambal basin
- Worked for Clean development mechanism project Involved Mapping forest area and analyzing changes in the forest cover over decades

#### **Education**

- 2017 Executive program Indian institute of Management, Calcutta
  - o Data Mining, Statistics, Time series Modelling, Machine learning
- 2011 M.Sc. in Geoinformatics, TERI University, Vasant Kunj, New Delhi
  - Core subjects: GIS and Remote Sensing, Statistics, Environmental modelling, Integrated Impact Assessment.
- 2009 Graduation from Delhi University